Welcome back to the second exercise series. First
up we have task three, where we should use the
first image from last week to build this small
sunrise sunset animation. So where do we start?
First we recreate the picture from
last week, some old definitions here,
so now since this is not a yellow
circle anymore but the sun, it might be
useful to actually call it that. Also, this is no
longer a green rectangle; it should be grass now.
Okay, so then we just say
we have the sun and grass,
and when we compile this, as we would expect,
we get the image from last week. Now the
plus template gives us some counter here to see
that we actually have the animation playing, but
as we would expect, there's nothing happening
yet. So first off, let's make the sun move,
so it moves in a circle. So it's probably a
good idea to actually use the rotated primitive,
which rotates
a picture around the coordinate origin. And then
to see what this is, let's use the coordinate
plane.
So if we have the origin here,
rotating the sun with the rotated
function will actually
rotate it around this origin
point, which is exactly the trajectory we
want the sun to take, so we use 'rotated'
and then some value. Let's just plug in
t for a second and see what's happening.
Okay, now it rotates counterclockwise because of
the way radians work, so if you want to mirror the
movement from the example, we just use
"minus t" to get the desired effect.
And now it moves in the other direction.
Okay, so now the problem is the sun is actually
on a layer higher than the grass, so we want the
sun to sink below the grass. So we need to put the
grass on a higher level, so to speak, than the sun.
Okay, then it will now vanish behind the grass,
but still, it continues to move around here,
on the bottom part of the image, which is
also something we don't want to happen.
So let's restrict the movement. How do
we do this? There are several ways.
First I will show you how to do it by
introducing a modified time parameter,
so I add a where clause, find this
t' and I just say, check whether t is
smaller than something.
Let's use pi for half a circle.
Then I use t, and if t is greater than
pi, then I use pi, so I fix this t
such that it no longer grows bigger than pi,
making the movement stop at some point. And then I
use this t' to rotate the sun over there. So
there's something wrong with this, which is
we're moving at the wrong half circle here. We're
starting here on the top and moving all the way
down here, but we actually would like to start
here and move over there. Okay, so why is that?
Obviously it's because we started the sun 6
units up here instead of this 6 over
here. So we just change this translation.
Like this, and now the sun starts behind the
grass, goes half a circle, and then sets behind the
grass again. Okay, so this is our basic animation.
Now, this is not the only way we can solve this.
We could, instead of modifying
the time parameter, say, okay,
we check the time and then either we have...
We have the sun.
We determine which image we want to render
here, so either we have the sun rotated
by -t, and let's no longer call this
t', but instead something like moving,
and we add this moving up here. And if we
are at the point where we would like to
stop the animation, we just use "blank", the
empty image, so nothing is rendered anymore.
And this will have the same effect.
But now, if we inspect this, there's no
sun anymore because there's this "blank"
image in the composition here after we've
done that change. Okay, so then what we
can also do is write this if expression inline,
precisely because if expressions in Haskell are
first-class expressions, so we don't
need this where clause necessarily,
might be good for structure, but you
can also just write it like this,
and again this is the same
animation. Now there's a fourth version. Probably
even more, but let's look at one more. If you
realize that actually, since this if-then-else is
kind of first-class here in Haskell, we can even
think about a slightly different version of
this. This with the changed t parameter,
because we could obviously
inline this here. So we would use something like
if
t is smaller than pi, then we
use minus t, as we use minus pi
to rotate the sun. And if we look at that,
sure enough, it's the same animation.
So now, if you look very closely,
you can see that we can probably take
this "minus" outside of this if. Also,
you can use the negate function here
to invert the sign of some expression. So,
this is kind of... this is exactly the same. And
now if we look really carefully at this if-then-else
expression, then we might realize that this is
basically: "If t is smaller than pi, it's t,
and otherwise, it's pi." So, what this
essentially is, is the minimum of t and pi.
And now I'm missing a parenthesis...
And we have the same animation and it
stops there. Now, if you look at this, the
tree view of this picture, we see that the sun
is blocked. It was hidden behind the grass there,
because it's always rotated by pi,
once pi exceeds... Uh, once t exceeds
pi. Yeah, this is a neat little
optimization we can do to fit this all into
one line and still be manageable to read.
Okay, that's that for task three.